Guide to the Anna Catherine Bahlmann Papers Relating to Edith Wharton
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Anna Catherine Bahlmann papers relating to Edith Wharton
1874-1917
YCAL MSS 361
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.05
(9 boxes) + 1 broadside folder.
The papers feature correspondence and personal effects relating to author Edith Wharton, including over 130 letters to Bahlmann from Wharton, dating from Bahlmann's employment to the Wharton family in 1874, as Edith's German language tutor, to 1915. The letters document a significant, long-standing relationship and shed light on Wharton's personal and literary affairs. In addition to the Wharton correspondence, there are single and small groups of letters between Bahlmann and family members, friends, and acquaintances, including William Morton Fullerton and Henry James, and a small number of third-party letters. Bahlmann's personal effects include legal and financial documents, notebooks, and writings, as well as material relating to Wharton. Other materials relating most directly to Wharton include clippings, documents on her work during the war, photographs, and postcards. Photographs consist of studio portraits of people and images of Wharton's residences. There are photographs of Wharton, Bahlmann family members, and friends, including Mary Cadwalader Jones. Wharton residences include "Reef Point" in Bar Harbour, Maine and the estate ("The Mount") in Lenox, Massachusetts.
Bahlmann, Anna Catherine, 1849-1916
Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Christie's, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile papers in Box 9 may be consulted only with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
Associated Materials
See also Edith Wharton Collection (YCAL MSS 42).
Anna Catherine Bahlmann (1849-1916) & Edith Wharton (1862-1937)
Anna Catherine Bahlmann was employed as Edith Wharton's German language tutor in 1874 and later served as her governess, secretary, and literary assistant.
Edith Wharton was a major American literary figure in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries and, though she is best known as a novelist and short-story writer, she also wrote poetry and non-fictional works on interior and landscape design. Wharton was the first woman to win the Pulitzer Prize, awarded in 1921 for her novel The Age of Innocence (1920). In addition to critical and bibliographic scholarship on Wharton, summary information is available in the standard print and online resources.
Scope and Contents
The papers feature correspondence and personal papers relating chiefly to author Edith Wharton, including over 130 letters to Bahlmann from Wharton, dating from her employment with the Wharton family in 1874, as Edith's German language tutor, to 1915. The letters document a significant, long-standing relationship and shed light on Wharton's personal and literary affairs. In addition to the Wharton correspondence, there are single and small groups of letters between Bahlmann and family members, friends, and acquaintances, including William Morton Fullerton and Henry James, and a small number of third-party letters. Bahlmann's personal papers include legal and financial documents, notebooks, and writings, as well as material relating to Edith Wharton. Other materials relating directly to Wharton include clippings, documents on her efforts during the war, a pressed lily, photographs, postcards, and a small sachet. Photographs consist of studio portraits of people and images of Wharton's residences. There are photographs of Wharton, dating from 1900 to 1905, family, and friends, including Mary Cadwalader Jones and Pauline Robinson. Wharton residences include "Reef Point" in Bar Harbour, Maine, 884 Park Avenue in New York, and the estate ("The Mount") in Lenox, Massachusetts.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1874-1917. II. Personal Papers, 1875-1916.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American; Bar Harbor (Me.); Lenox (Mass.); Photographic prints; Studio portraits; Authors; Bahlmann, Anna Catherine, 1849-1916; Fullerton, William Morton, 1865-1952; James, Henry, 1843-1916; Jones, Mary Cadwalader; Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937
- Correspondence, 1874-1917; Series I; 0.84' (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subseries: General Correspondence and Third Party Correspondence.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, contains letters to and from Anna Bahlmann and between others. General Correspondence includes single and small groups of letters between Bahlmann and family members, friends, and acquaintances, such as William Morton Fullerton and Henry James, and features over 130 letters to Bahlmann from Edith Wharton.
  Bahlmann was employed as Wharton's tutor in 1874, when Edith was only 12, and later served as her secretary and literary assistant. Wharton's letters, which date from 1874 to 1915, spanning over four decades, document her reading and education, literary work and acquaintances, travels, and impressions on such topics as art, architecture, and landscape design. The letters document an important, long-standing relationship and shed light on Wharton's personal and literary affairs. The correspondence, unpublished in 2010, contains a significant number of early or youthful letters, filling a gap in Wharton's published correspondence.
  Third-party correspondence, arranged alphabetically by correspondent, consists chiefly of condolence letters to Bahlmann's niece, Mrs. Charles Parker (Anna Louise Bahlmann Parker), including several letters from Wharton.
  In addition to the correspondence in Series I, several autograph postcards, from Wharton and others, have been preserved in the postcard albums in Series II. Personal Papers. Cross references are provided where appropriate in the box and folder list below.
  Correspondence is chiefly in English, with some letters in French and German. Many letters are accompanied by transcriptions.
  - General Correspondence
    - Abbott, [Myra], 1882 June 26 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bahlmann, William F., 1897-1915, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - [Banas?], A. S. de, 1880-1881 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Breitsprecher, Anna, 1902, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Collez, B., 1916 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Duchon, Henri, 1915 February (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Fullerton, [Willliam?] Morton, 1914 March 29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Hase, Albertina, 1902-1903 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - James, Henry, 1905 August 14 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Jones, M[ary] C[adwalader], 1916 April 4 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - [Parker, Anna?], undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Parker, Charles, [1905?] (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Parker, Mrs. Charles, 1905, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Parker, William B[ahlmann], 1913, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Robinson, Pauline, 1903-1910 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
    - "Rodier", 1915 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Rutherfurd, Lewis, 1876, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - [Rutherfurd, Margaret?], undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Rutherfurd, Winthrop, 1875, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Stuyvesant, Mary R., 1874-1879, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Van Rensselaer, Louisa, 1915 August 19 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Wharton, Edith, 1874-1915, undated (Box 2, Folder 23-37)
      Includes vendor inventory
    - Wharton, Edith (transcriptions), 1874-1917, undated (Box 3, Folder 38-39)
    - Christmas cards, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Unidentified, 1884-1915, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Third Party Correspondence
    - Fuller, Henry B. to W. L.. Moody (copy), [1902 March 27] (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Jones, Mary Cadwalader to Mrs. Charles Parker, 1916 April (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Masten & Nichols to Mrs. Charles S. Parker, 1916 April 25 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      Includes copy of Anna Bahlmann's will
    - Parker, Florence to "Laura", undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Robinson, Pauline to Mrs. Charles Parker, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Wharton, Edith to Mrs. Charles Parker, 1916-1917 (Box 3, Folder 47)
- Personal Papers, 1875-1916; Series II; 1.46' (4 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series II, Personal Papers, contains Anna Bahlmann's personal papers, some of which relate to Edith Wharton.
  Materials relating directly to Wharton include clippings, documents on her efforts during the war, a pressed lily, photographs, postcards, and a small sachet. Photographs consist of studio portraits of people, mostly women, and images of Wharton's residences. There are photographs of Wharton, dating from 1900 to 1905, family, and friends, including Mary Cadwalader Jones and Pauline Robinson. Wharton residences include "Reef Point" in Bar Harbour, Maine, 884 Park Avenue in New York, and the estate ("The Mount") in Lenox, Massachusetts.
  Postcards, some dating from a trip Wharton and Bahlmann took to North Africa in 1914, have been removed from two albums and the order preserved. The albums have been digitized, and images of the albums and individual postcards, front and back, can be found online through Beinecke's Digital Library. Several postcards are inscribed by Wharton and others.
  Anna Bahlmann's papers include legal and financial documents, notebooks, and writings.
  - Inventory of Anna Catherine Bahlmann's personal effects, undated (Box 4, Folder 47a)
  - Boards [from photo album?], undated (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Clippings, 1898-1914, undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Edith Wharton's war work, 1915-1916 (Box 4, Folder 50-51)
  - Handwriting sample and analysis, 1884-1894 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Last will and testament and codicil, 1910-1916 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Ledgers, 1898-1916 (Box 4, Folder 54-55)
  - Lily and leaf, 1885, undated (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - List [of contributions?], undated (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Manuscript fragments, undated (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Notebooks, 1886, undated (Box 5, Folder 59-61)
  - Obituary notice from Kansas City Star, 1916 April (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Passport, 1914 December (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Photographs, 1876-1905 (Box 5, Folder 64-66)
    Includes photographs by Arnold Genthe and others
  - Postcard albums, 1909-1910, undated (Box 5, Folder 67-116)
    Includes photographs and correspondence
  - Postcard albums, 1904-19[12?], undated (Box 6, Folder 117-209a)
  - Postcards albums, undated (Box 7, Folder 210-260)
  - Postcards (loose), undated (Box 7, Folder 261)
  - Printed ephemera, 1876-1913, undated (Box 7, Folder 262)
  - Receipts, 1916 April 18 (Box 7, Folder 263)
  - Sachet, 1875 (Box 7, Folder 264)
  - Writings by Anna Bahlmann, undated (Box 7, Folder 265-268)
    Includes typescript drafts for "A Belated Remedy," "Counsins," and "The Edith Wharton Relief Work"
  - Writings by others, 1905-1907, undated (Box 7, Folder 269-277)
- Oversize, 1900-1914; 1.34' (1 box)
  - Clippings (In Series II), 1902-1914, undated (Box 278 (Broadside))
  - Photographs (In Series II), 1900, undated (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 279-289)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 1900-1914; 0.42' (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Clippings from correspondence (In Series I) (Box 9, Folder 290-292)
  - Postcard albums (In Series II) (Box 9, Folder 293-294)